Hey guys.
مرحباً يا اصدقاء
It's funny, someone just mentioned MacGyver,
انه مضحك, شخص ما ذكر للتو ماكجايڨر,
because that was, like, I loved it,
لأن ذلك كان، مثل، وأنا أحب ذلك،
and when I was seven, I taped a fork to a drill
و عندما كنت في السابعة من عمري، قمت بتركيب شوكة طعام بالة حفر
and I was like, "Hey, Mom, I'm going to Olive Garden."
و قد كنت كـ "يا امي، انا ذاهب الى مزرعة الزيتون."
And -- (Drilling noise) (Laughter)
و--(صوت آلة الحفر) (ضحك)
And it worked really well there.
وقد عملت بشكل جيد حقا هناك.
And you know, it had a profound effect on me.
و كما تعرف, كان لها اثر عميق في نفسي
It sounds silly, but I thought, okay,
قد تبدو سخيفة, لكنني فكرت,
the way the world works can be changed,
الطريقة التي يعمل بها العالم يمكن ان تتغير,
and it can be changed by me in these small ways.
و يمكن ان تتغير بواسطتي بهذه الطرق الصغيرة.
And my relationship to
و علاقتي بـ..
especially human-made objects
خاصة الأغراض التي صنعها الانسان
which someone else said they work like this,
و التي تم تحديد طريقة عملها بواسطة شخص اَخر،
well, I can say they work a different way, a little bit.
كذلك يمكنني ان اقول انها تعمل بطريقة مختلفة، قليلاً.
And so, about 20 years later,
وهكذا، بعد ما يقارب 20 سنة،
I didn't realize the full effect of this,
لم ادرك التاَثير الكليٌ لهذا،
but I went to Costa Rica
لكنيٌ ذهبت لكوستاريكا
and I stayed with these Guaymí natives there,
و مكثت مع افراد من قبيلة قوامي الاصليين هناك،
and they could pull leaves off of trees and make shingles out of them,
وبإمكانهم قطف صفق من الشجر و صنع القوباء من الصفق،
and they could make beds out of trees,
وبإمكانهم صنع اسرّة من الشجر،
and they could -- I watched this woman for three days.
و بالفعل يمكنهم، لقد شاهدت هذه المرأة لثلاثة ايام.
I was there. She was peeling this palm frond apart,
لقد كنت هناك. كانت تقوم بتقشير سعف النخيل،
these little threads off of it, and she'd roll the threads together
تلك الخيوط الصغيرة من سعف النخيل، و تقوم بلف الخيوط مع بعضها
and make little thicker threads, like strings,
لتنتج خيوط اتخن، كالحبال.
and she would weave the strings together,
و تقوم بنسج الحبال مع بعضها،
and as the materiality of this exact very bag
و بنفس المواد المصنعة لهذه الحقيبة
formed before my eyes over those three days,
صُنعت امام عيناي في تلك الايام الثلاثة،
the materiality of the way the world works,
المادية التي يعمل بها هذا العالم،
of reality, kind of started to unravel in my mind,
من الواقع، نوعاً ما بدأت بالظهور في عقلي،
because I realized that this bag and these clothes
لأنني ادركت ان هذه الحقيبة تلك الملابس
and the trampoline you have at home and the pencil sharpener,
و لعبة القفز لديك في منزلك و المبراة،
everything you have is made out of either a tree or a rock
مل ما تمتلك قم تم تصنيعه من الشجر او الاحجار
or something we dug out of the ground and did some process to,
او شئ قمنا بإستخراجه من الارض و قمنا بإجراء عمليات عليه،
maybe a more complicated one, but still, everything was made that way.
ربما تكون معقدة اكثر، لكن مع ذلك، كل شئ تم صنعه بتلك الطريقة.
And so I had to start studying,
و بذلك كان يجب ان ابدأ الدراسة،
who is it that's making these decisions?
من الذي يقوم بإتخاذ تلك القرارات؟
Who's making these things? How did they make them?
من الذي يقوم بصنع تلك الاشياء؟ و كيف قاموا بذلك؟
What stops us from making them?
ما الذي يمنعنا من صنعها؟
Because this is how reality is created.
ذلك لأنها هى الطريقة التي خُلق بها الواقع.
So I started right away. I was at MIT Media Lab,
لذلك بدأت على الفور. لقد كنت بداخل معمل وسائل اعلام معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنلوچيا.
and I was studying the maker movement
و كنت ادرس حركات الصانع
and makers and creativity.
و الصانع و الابداع.
And I started in nature, because I saw these Guaymís
و بدأت بالطبيعة، ذلك لأني رأيت القواميز
doing it in nature, and there just seems to be less barriers.
يعملون في الطبيعة، و هنالك على ما يبدو الحواجز اقل.
So I went to Vermont to Not Back to School Camp,
هكذا ذهبت لولاية فيرمونت لمخيم المدرسة،
where there's unschoolers who are just kind of hanging out
حيث هنالك غير المدرسيين الذين يقومون بالتواجد فقط
and willing to try anything.
و مستعدون لتجربة اي شئ
So I said, "Let's go into the woods near this stream
فقلت لهم، "لنذهب الى الغابة قرب هذا المكان
and just put stuff together, you know, make something,
و فقط نقوم بوضع اشياء مع بعضها، انتم تعلمون، نصنع شيئاً
I don't care, geometrical shapes, just grab some junk from around you.
لا تهمني الاشكال الهندسية، فقط قم بإستخدام الاغراض غير المرغوب بها من حولك.
We won't bring anything with us.
لن نجلب معنا شئ.
And, like, within minutes, this is very easy for adults
و في غضون دقائق، هذا عمل سهلُ جداً للكبار
and teens to do.
و المراهقين
Here's a triangle that was being formed underneath a flowing stream,
و هنا مثلث و الذي كان يجري تشكيله تحت تيار جاري،
and the shape of an oak leaf being made
و شكل ورقة البلوط يتم عملها
by other small oak leaves being put together.
بواسطة اوراق بلوط صغيرة يتم وضعها مع بعضها.
A leaf tied to a stick with a blade of grass.
ورقة رُبطت مع عصاة بشفرة من العشب.
The materiality and fleshiness and meat of the mushroom
مادية و بدانة و لحم المشروم
being explored by how it can hold up different objects being stuck into it.
يتم استكشافها بإمكانيتها على تثبيت اغراض مختلفة يتم تثيتها عليها.
And after about 45 minutes, you get really intricate projects
و بعد ما يقارب 45 دقيقة، تتحصل على مشاريع معقدة بالفعل
like leaves sorted by hue, so you get a color fade
مثل اوراق منظمة بالمسح، حتى تحصل على لون متلاشي
and put in a circle like a wreath.
و تضعه في دائرة كإكليل.
And the creator of this, he said,
و قال صانه هذا الإكليل
"This is fire. I call this fire."
"هذه نار. انا اسميها نار."
And someone asked him, "How do you get those sticks
و يسأله شخص "كيف يمكنك ان تجعل هذه الاعواد
to stay on that tree?"
تثبت على تلك الشجرة"
And he's like, "I don't know, but I can show you."
"لا اعرف، لكن يمكنني ان اُريك كيف."
And I'm like, "Wow, that's really amazing.
و انا كنت، " واو، هذا مدهش حقاَ.
He doesn't know, but he can show you."
هو لا يعرف كيف، لكن بإمكانه ان يريك."
So his hands know and his intuition knows,
يديه و حدسه يعرفان،
but sometimes what we know gets in the way
لكن احياناً الذي نعلمه يقف في طريقنا
of what could be, especially
مما يمكن ان يكون، خاصةً
when it comes to the human-made, human-built world.
عندما يتعلق الامر بالصناعات و البنايات البشرية
We think we already know how something works,
نفكر اننا نعلم كيف تعمل الاشياء،
so we can't imagine how it could work.
لذلك لا نستطيع التخيل كيف يمكن ان تعمل.
We know how it's supposed to work,
نعلم كيف من المفترض ان تعمل،
so we can't suppose all the things that could be possible.
لذلك لا نستطيع ان نفترض كل الاشياء التي يمكن ان تكون ممكنة.
So kids don't have as hard of a time with this,
لذلك الاطفال لا يجدون نفس الصعوبة مع هذا،
and I saw in my own son, I gave him this book.
و قد شاهدت ذلك في ابني، اعطيته هذا الكتاب.
I'm a good hippie dad, so I'm like,
انا اب هيپي جيد، لذلك قد كنت،
"Okay, you're going to learn to love the moon.
"حسناً، سوف تتعلم ان تحب القمر.
I'm going to give you some building blocks
سأعطيك بعض مكعبات البناء
and they're nonrectilinear cactus building blocks,
و هي مكعبات بناء صبارية ليست مستقيمة الخطوط،
so it's totally legit."
هكذا هى شرعية تماماً
But he doesn't really know what to do with these.
لكنه لا يعرف ماذا يفعل بها
I didn't show him.
لم اريه.
And so he's like, "Okay, I'll just mess around with this."
و هكذا قد كان، " حسناً، سوف اعبث بها."
This is no different than the sticks are to the teens in the forest.
و هذا لا يختلف عن الاعواد للمراهقين في الغابة.
Just going to try to put them in shapes
فقط سيحاول وضعها على الاشكال
and push on them and stuff.
و يضغط عليهم
And before long, he's kind of got this mechanism
و قبل وقت طويل، نوعاً ما قد حصل على هذه الاَلية
where you can almost launch and catapult objects around,
حيث يمكنك انشاء و اطلاق الاغراض هنا و هناك
and he enlists us in helping him.
و ينتقينا لمساعدته.
And at this point, I'm starting to wonder,
و في تلك النقطة، بدأت اتساءل،
what kind of tools can we give people,
ما هو نوع الادوات التي يمكن ان نعطيها للناس،
especially adults, who know too much,
خاصة الكبار، الذين يعلمون اكثر من اللازم،
so that they can see the world as malleable,
حتى يمكنهم رؤية العالم كقبّال للتغيير
so they see themselves as agents of change
حتى يروا انفسهم كعوامل للتغيير
in their everyday lives.
في حياتهم اليومية.
Because the most advanced scientists are really
ذلك لأن معظم العلماء المتقدمون هم في الحقيقة
just kind of pushing the way the world itself works,
يضغطون على الطريقة التي يعمل بها العالم نفسه،
pushing what matter can do,
يضغطون على ما يمكن ان تعمله الماده،
the most advanced artists are just pushing the medium,
اكثر الفنانون تطوراً فقط يقومون بالضغط على الوسط،
and any sufficiently complicated task,
و اى مهمة معقدة بما فيه الكفاية،
whether you're a cook or a carpenter or you're raising a child --
سواء ان كنت طباخ او نجار او تربي طفلاً
anything that's complicated --
اي شئ معقد
comes up with problems that aren't solved in the middle of it,
يأتي بمشاكل غير محلولة في داخلها،
and you can't do a good job getting it done unless you can say,
و انت لا تستطيع ان تعمل عملاً جيداً بدون ان تقول،
"Okay, well we're just going to have to refigure this.
"حسناً، يجب علينا ان نعيد فهم هذا.
I don't care that pencils are supposed to be for writing.
لا اهتم ان كانت الاقلام يفترض ان نكتب بها.
I'm going to use them a different way."
سوف اقوم بإستعمالها بطريقة اخرى."
So let me show you a little demo.
فدعني اريك عرض صغير.
This is a little piano circuit right in here,
هذه دائرة كهربية لبيانو صغير،
and this is an ordinary paintbrush
و هذه فرشاة تلوين عادية
that I smashed it together with. (Beeping)
و التي قمت بضغطها مع بعضها ب. (بيييب)
And so, with some ketchup,
و هكذا، ببعض الكاتشب،
— (musical notes) —
(نوتة موسيقية)
and then I can kind of
و عندها نوعاً ما استطيع
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفييق)
And that's awesome, right?
و هذا رائع، اليس كذلك؟
But this is not what's awesome.
لكن الرائع ليس هذا.
What's awesome is what happens
الرائع الذي يحدث
when you give the piano circuit to people.
عندما تعطي دائرة البيانو الكهربية للأشخاص.
A pencil is not just a pencil.
قلم الرصاص ليس فقط قلم رصاص
Look what it has in the middle of it.
انظر لمنتصفه.
That's a wire running down the middle,
هذا سلك في منتصفه،
and not only is it a wire,
و ليس فقط سلك
if you take that piano circuit, you can thumbtack
اذا اخذت دائرة البيانو، يمكنك وضعها و لصقها
into the middle of a pencil,
بداخل منتصف قلم الرصاص
and you can lay out wire on the page, too,
و يمكنك وضع سلك على الصفحة ايضاً،
and get electrical current to run through it.
و تمرير تيار كهربي عبرها
And so you can kind of hack a pencil,
و هكذا يمكنك اختراق (هاك) قلم الرصاص نوعاً ما،
just by thumbtacking into it with a little piano electrical circuit.
فقط بوضع دائرة كهربية لبيانو صغير.
And the electricity runs through your body too.
و تمر الكهرباء عبر جسدك ايضاً.
And then you can take the little piano circuit off the pencil.
و عندها تستطيع اخذ دائرة البيانو الصغير من قلم الرصاص.
You can make one of these brushes just on the fly.
يمكنك صنع احد هذه الفرش على الطاير.
All you do is connect to the bristles,
كل ما عليك فعله هو توصيل الشعيرات،
and the bristles are wet, so they conduct,
و الشعيرات مبللة لذلك توصل لاكهرباء،
and the person's body conducts,
و جسم الانسان يوصل ايضاً،
and leather is great to paint on,
و الجلد جيد للتلوين عليه،
and then you can start hooking to everything,
و عندها يمكنك التوصيل بأي شئ،
even the kitchen sink.
حتى حوض المطبخ.
The metal in the sink is conductive.
المعدن الموجود في الحوض موصل.
Flowing water acts like a theremin or a violin.
الماء الجاري يعمل مثل آلة الكمان.
(Musical notes)
(نوتة موسيقية)
And you can even hook to the trees.
يمكنك ايضاً التوصيل بالاشجار.
Anything in the world is either conductive or not conductive,
اي شئ في العالم اما موصل او غير موصل،
and you can use those together.
يمكنك استخدامهم سوياً.
So — (Laughter) —
حتى... (ضحك)
I took this to those same teens, because those teens are
اخذت هذا لنفس المراهقين، لأنهم..
really awesome, and they'll try things that I won't try.
حقاً رائعون، سيجربون اشياء لن اجربها.
I don't even have access to a facial piercing if I wanted to.
انا حتى لا املك الوصول الى ثقب الوجه ان اردت.
And this young woman, she made what she called a hula-looper,
و هذه المرأة الشابة، صنعت ما تسميه (هولا لوبر)،
and as the hula hoop traveled around her body,
و كما تحركت طارة الهولا حول جسدها،
she has a circuit taped to her shirt right there.
لديها دائرة ملصقة حول قميصها،
You can see her pointing to it in the picture.
يمكنك رؤيتها تشير الى الدائرة في الصورة.
And every time the hula hoop would smush against her body,
و كل ما تضغط الطارة على الدائرة الكهربية،
it would connect two little pieces of copper tape,
تتوصل قطعتان من شريط النحاس
and it would make a sound, and the next sound,
و تصدر صوتاً،
and it would loop the same sounds over and over again.
و يتكرر نفس الصوت كل مرة
I ran these workshops everywhere.
قمت بإدارة هذه الورشة في كل مكان
In Taiwan, at an art museum, this 12-year-old girl
في تايوان، في متحف فني، هذه الفتاة ذات الـ 12 عاماً
made a mushroom organ out of some mushrooms that were from Taiwan
صنعت اورقان عش الغراب (فطر) من اعشاش غراب من تايوان
and some electrical tape and hot glue.
و شريط كهرباء و بعض الصمغ الساخن.
And professional designers were making artifacts
و المصممون المحترفون كانوا يصنعون تحف فنية
with this thing strapped onto it.
بهذا الشئ مدبس حوله.
And big companies like Intel
و شركات كبيرة كشركة آنتل
or smaller design firms like Ideo or startups like Bump,
او اخرى اصغر كـ إديو او شركات جديدة كـ بمپ،
were inviting me to give workshops,
كانوا يدعونني لأعطي ورشات عمل
just to practice this idea of smashing electronics
فقط لتدريب فكرة خلط الالكترونيات
and everyday objects together.
بالأغراض اليومية
And then we came up with this idea
و عندها توصلنا على هذه الفكرة
to not just use electronics,
ليس فقط استخدام الالكترونيات،
but let's just smash computers with everyday objects
لكن خلط الحاسوب بالاغراض اليومية
and see how that goes over.
و مشاهدة ما سيحدث
And so I just want to do a quick demo.
و هكذا فقط اردت ان اقوم بعرض سريع.
So this is the MaKey MaKey circuit,
هذه دائرة ماكيي ماكيي
and I'm just going to set it up from the beginning in front of you.
سأقوم بتركيبها من البداية امامكم.
So I'll just plug it in, and now it's on by USB.
سأقوم بتوصيلها، الان هي موصلة بواسطة (USB)
And I'll just hook up the forward arrow.
و سأقوم فقط بتوصيل السهم الامامي.
You guys are facing that way, so I'll hook it to this one.
انتم مواجهون تلك الناحية، لذا سأوصل هذه.
And I'll just hook up a little ground wire to it.
و سأقوم بتأريضه
And now, if I touch this piece of pizza,
الان، اذا لمست قطعة البيزا هذه
the slides that I showed you before should go forward.
الشرائح التي اريتكم اياها من قبل ستتحرك للأمام.
And now if I hook up this wire just by connecting it
و الآن اذا قمت بتوصيل هذا السلك
to the left arrow, I'm kind of programming it by where I hook it up,
الى السهم اليسار، انا اقوم ببرمجته نوعاً ما بالمكان الذي اقوم بالتوصيل منه،
now I have a left arrow and a right arrow,
الان لدي سهم يسار و سهم يمين،
so I should be able to go forwards and backwards
لذلك ينبغي ان تكون قادرة على التحرك الى الامام و الى الخلف
and forwards and backwards. Awesome.
و الى الامام و الى الخلف، رائع.
And so we're like, "We gotta put a video out about this."
و هكذا قد كنا ك "يجب وضع ڨديو عن هذا."
Because no one really believed that this was important
لأنه لم يكن هنالك شخص يؤمن ان هذا مهم
or meaningful except me and, like, one other guy.
أو أنه ذا معنى في ما عداي و شخص آخر.
So we made a video to prove that
لذا قمنا بتصوير فيديو لأثبات ان
there's lots of stuff you can do.
هنالك كثير من الاشياء يمكنك عملها.
You can kind of sketch with Play-Doh
يمكنك ان ترسم بإستخدام (play Doh)
and just Google for game controllers.
و فقط قوقل لوحدات التحكم في اللعبة.
Just ordinary Play-Doh, nothing special.
فقط (Play Doh) عادية، لا شئ اكثر
And you can literally draw joysticks
و يمكنك حرفياً رسم عصا التحكم
and just find Pacman on your computer and then just hook it up. (Video game noises)
و توصيلها على حاسوبك و لعب پاك مان. (اصوات العاب الفيديو)
And you know the little plastic drawers you can get at Target?
و انت تعرف ادراج الپلاستيك الصغيرة التي يمكن ان تحصل عليها من (تارقت)؟
Well, if you take those out, they hold water great,
اذا اخذتهم، يمكنهم حفظ الماء بصورة جيدة،
but you can totally cut your toes,
لكن يمكنك تماماً قطع اصابعك،
so yeah, just be careful.
كن حذراً
You know the Happiness Project, where the experts
انت تعرف مشروع السعادة، حيث الخبراء
are setting up the piano stairs, and how cool that is?
يقومون بتركيب سلم الپيانو، و كم رائع ذلك؟
Well, I think it's cool,
اظن ذلك جيداً،
but we should be doing that stuff ourselves.
لكن يجب علينا ان نفعل تلك الاشياء بنفسنا
It shouldn't be a set of experts engineering the way the world works.
لا يجب ان يكونوا مجموعة من المهندسين الخبراء كما يعمل العالم.
We should all be participating
ينبغي علينا جميعاً المشاركة
in changing the way the world works together.
في تغيير الطريقة التي يعمل بها العالم سوياً.
Aluminum foil. Everybody has a cat.
ورق الالمنيوم. الكل لديه قِط.
Get a bowl of water. This is just Photo Booth on your Mac OS.
احضر وعاء من الماء. هذا فقط (photo booth) بجهاز (mac os).
Hover the mouse over the "take a photo" button,
قم بتحريك المؤشر فوق ايقونة (take a photo)
and you've got a little cat photo booth.
و الان لديك كشك صور القط صغير
And so we needed hundreds of people to buy this.
قد احتجنا لمئات من الاشخاص أن يشتروا هذا.
If hundreds of people didn't buy this, we couldn't put it on the market.
اذا لم يشتريه المئات لا يمكننا وضعه في السوق.
And so we put it up on Kickstarter,
و هكذا وضعناه في (kickstarter)
and hundreds of people bought it in the first day.
المئات من الاشخاص اشتروه في اليوم الاول.
And then 30 days later,
و بعد 30 يوم
11,000 people had backed the project.
11،000 من الاشخاص قاموا بإختراق المشروع.
And then what the best part is, we started getting
و افضل ما في ذلك، بدأنا في الحصول على
a flood of videos in of people doing crazy things with it.
الكثير من الڨيديوهات لأشخاص يفعلون اشياء مجنونة بها.
So this is "The Star-Spangled Banner" by eating lunch,
هذا هو "شعار نجمة لامعة" من خلال تناول الغداء
including drinking Listerine.
بالأضافة الى شرب الليسترين.
And we actually sent this guy materials.
و في الواقع قمنا بإرسال مواد لهذا الشخص.
We're like, "We're sponsoring you, man.
قد كنا، "نحن نرعاك يا رجل.
You're, like, a pro maker."
انت كصانع محترف."
Okay, just wait for this one. This is good.
حسناً، فقط انتظر هذه انها جيدة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And these guys at the exploratorium are
و هؤلاء الشباب في الاستكشافية
playing house plants as if they were drums.
يلعبان بنباتات المنزل كما ان كانت طبول.
And dads and daughters are completing circuits in special ways.
الآباء و البنات يكملون دوائر بطرق خاصة.
And then this brother -- look at this diagram.
و عندها هذا الاخانظروا الى هذا الرسم البياني.
See where it says "sister"?
انظروا حيث تقول "اخوات"؟.
I love when people put humans on the diagram.
احب عندما يضع الاشخاص بشر على الرسم البياني
I always add humans to any technical --
دائماً اضيف البشر الى اي تكنيك
if you're drawing a technical diagram, put a human in it.
اذا كنت ترسم رسم بياني تقني، ضع فيه انسان
And this kid is so sweet. He made this trampoline slideshow advancer for his sister
و هذا الطفل حلو جداً، قام بعمل عرض شرائح للعبة القفز لأخته
so that on her birthday, she could be the star of the show,
و ذلك حتى يكون نجم الحفل في عيد ميلادها
jumping on the trampoline to advance the slides.
يقفز على لعبة القفز حتى يتقدم في الشرائح.
And this guy rounded up his dogs and he made a dog piano.
و هذا الشخص وضع كلابه على شكل دائرة و قام بصنع پيانو كلبي
And this is fun,
و هذا ممتع،
and what could be more useful than feeling alive and fun?
و ماذا يمكن ان يكون اكثر إفادة من الاحساس بالحياة و المرح
But it's also very serious because
لكنه ايضاً جاد جداً لأن
all this accessibility stuff started coming up,
كل الاشياء التي يمكن الوصول اليها بدأت بالظهور،
where people can't use computers, necessarily.
حيث الناس لا يمكنهم استعمال الحواسيب بالضرورة.
Like this dad who wrote us, his son has cerebral palsy
كهذا الاب الذي كتب لنا ان ابنه مصاب بالشلل الدماغي
and he can't use a normal keyboard.
و لا يمكنه استعمال لوحة المفاتيح العادية.
And so his dad couldn't necessarily afford
و هو لا يمكنه بالضرورة تحمل تكلفة
to buy all these custom controllers.
شراء وحدات تحكم خاصة.
And so, with the MaKey MaKey, he planned to make
و هكذا بواسطة ماكيي ماكيي، خطط ان يعمل
these gloves to allow him to navigate the web.
قفازات تسمح لإبنه ان يتصفح الشبكة
And a huge eruption of discussion
و ثوران كبير للمناقشة
around accessibility came, and we're really excited about that.
حول امكانية الوصول، و نحن متحمسون جداً لذلك
We didn't plan for that at all.
لم نخطط لذلك ابداً
And then all these professional musicians started using it,
و عندها بدأ كل هؤلاء الموسيقيين المحترفين بإستخدامه
like at Coachella, just this weekend
مثل عند كوتشيلا. في عطلة الاسبوع الاسبوع الماضي
Jurassic 5 was using this onstage,
چراسيك 5 استخدموه في المسرح.
and this D.J. is just from Brooklyn, right around here,
و هذا الدي چي من بروكلين. من هنا
and he put this up last month.
و قام ببناء هذا الشهر الماضي
And I love the carrot on the turntable.
احب الجزرة على القرص الدوار.
(Music: Massive Attack — "Teardrop")
(موسيقى: Massive Attack="Tear drop")
Most people cannot play them that way. (Laughter)
معظم الناس لا يمكنهم العزف عليهم بتلك الطريقة (ضحك)
And when this started to get serious,
و عندما اصبح هذا جاداً،
I thought, I'd better put a really serious warning label on the box that this comes in,
فكرت انه من الافضل وضع علامة تحذير جادة على العلبة التي يأتي بها الجهاز.
because otherwise people are going to be getting this
و ذلك لأنه عدا ذلك سوف يتحصل الناس على هذا
and they're going to be turning into agents of creative change,
و سوف يتحولون الى عوامل للتغيير الابداعية،
and governments will be crumbling,
و الحكومات ستتكوم على نفسها
and I wouldn't have told people, so I thought I'd better warn them.
و لم اكن لأقول للناس، ففكرت انه من الافضل تحذيرهم.
And I also put this little surprise. When you open the lid
و ايضاً قمت بعمل هذه المفاجئة الصغيرة. عندما تفتح الغطاء
of the box, it says, "The world is a construction kit."
العلبة، ستقول "العالم هو مجموعة بناء."
And as you start to mess around this way,
و حين تبدأ باللعب حول هذه الطريقة،
I think that, in some small ways, you do start to see
افكر ان، بطرق صغيرة انت تبدأ برؤية
the landscape of your everyday life
المناظر في حياتك اليومية
a little bit more like something you could express yourself with,
كأنه شيئ يمكنك ان تعبر به عن نفسك
and a little bit more like you could participate
و قليلاً يمكنك ان تشارك
in designing the future of the way the world works.
بتصميم المستقبل بالطريقة التي يعمل بها العالم.
And so next time you're on an escalator
و في المرة القادمة و انت في السلم المتحرك
and you drop an M&amp;M by accident,
و تقع منك حبة إم اند إم بدون قصد
you know, maybe that's an M&amp;M surfboard, not an escalator,
انت تعلم ربما ذلك عبارة عن مزلجة إم اند إم و ليس سلم متحرك
so don't pick it up right away.
لذا لا ترفعها فوراً.
Maybe take some more stuff out of your pockets
خذ مزيد من الاغراض من جيبك
and throw it down, and maybe some chapstick, whatever.
و ارمهم، ربما قليل من التشاب ستيك او اي شيئ
I used to want to design a utopian society
كنت اريد ان اصمم مجتمع طوباوي
or a perfect world or something like that.
او عالم مثالي او ما شابه ذلك.
But as I'm kind of getting older
لكن كما انني ازيد في العمر
and kind of messing with all this stuff,
و اقوم باللعب بهذه الاغراض
I'm realizing that my idea of a perfect world
انا ادرك ان فكرتي عن العالم المثالي
really can't be designed by one person
لا يمكن ان ثصمم بواسطة شخص واحد
or even by a million experts.
او حتى مليون خبير
It's really going to be seven billion pairs of hands,
يجب ان تكون 7 بليون زوج من الايادي
each following their own passions,
الكل يسري خلف شغفه
and each kind of like a mosaic coming up
و كل منهم كفسيفساء قادمة
and creating this world in their backyards
و تخلق هذا العالم في الفناء الخلفي
and in their kitchens.
و في مطابخهم.
And that's the world I really want to live in.
هذا هو العالم الذي ارغب بالعيش فيه
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)